Good morning, today's דף Daf is ד, Dalet, and we pick up
two lines from the bottom on ג עמוד ב, Gimmel Amud Bet,
and we have gone through the different explanations of the problem of
סוכה Sukkah being higher than 20 אמות, Amot, and we've also had
an opportunity to look at one of the core debates about the
minimum size of a סוכה, Sukkah, is it to be able to
contain your body and your head and your שולחן, Shulchan, a small
little tray table which is about seven and a half טפחים Tefachim
by seven and a half טפחים, Tefachim, about two feet by two
feet roughly, or do you need it to be the size of
ד אמות על ד אמות, Arba Amot by Arba Amot, which is
רבי'ס Rebbi's position, about six feet by six feet? And the גמרא
Gemara said when it comes to defining a house, everybody agrees like
a more permanent place that a minimum size is six feet by
six feet. There's some people said like a Manhattan studio apartment. But
the question is by a סוכה. Sukkah. Is a סוכה Sukkah defined
as a דירת עראי, Dirat Arai, temporary dwelling, and in that way
it's a contrast to your house because your house is permanent and
your סוכה Sukkah is temporary and therefore a smaller size suffices, or
does it have to be a substitute for your house and therefore
it also requires the ד אמות על ד אמות? Arba Amot by
Arba Amot? Is סוכה דירת קבע Sukkah Dirat Keva or דירת עראי,
Dirat Arai, permanent or temporary? A very important debate here translated into
the question of the minimum dimensions, at least width and length. Now
we get to a series of sort of cases to relating to
the issue of minimum height and also maximum height and also as
we will see the issue of minimum height. So let's take a
look. Two lines from the bottom on ג עמוד ב. Gimmel Amud
Bet. היתה גבוהה מעשרים אמה. Hai sukkah gevoha me-esrim amah. If the
סוכה Sukkah was higher than 20 אמות, Amot, ובא למעטה, u-va le-ma-ata,
and you are coming to try to lower it, right? So you
want to fix the problem; it's higher than 20 אמות Amot and
you want to actually lower the height. Now it's a lot, that's
a little bit hard, like what do you do? You take off
the סכך, Schach, you trim the walls, you put the סכך Schach
back on? So here's some interesting suggestions about how you can lower
the height. So ובא למעטה, u-va le-ma-ata, you want to lower it,
בכרים וכסתות, bekrim ve-ksasot, with pillows and blankets. Don't lower the ceiling,
raise the floor! It's a lot easier. Okay. So put stuff, put
pillows and blankets on the floor and then the actual height from
floor to ceiling will be less, because you will remember this is
important that we have discussed the question of whether the height is
measured as an interior height or the exterior height, and because for
the most part the problems of too high have been emphasizing the
height of the סכך, Schach, although again there have been different opinions,
the assumption here is is that the height is measured as the
interior height from the floor to the base of the סכך. Schach.
That the base of the סכך, Schach, let's just say, cannot be
higher than 20 אמות. Amot. So therefore raise the floor and you
will solve the problem that way. Okay. So היתה גבוהה, hai sukkah
gevoha, לא הוי מיעוט, lo hava miut, that doesn't count. Pillows and
blankets don't become part of the floor. They're like on the floor
but they don't redefine what the floor is. ואף על גב דבטלינהו,
Ve-af al gav de-vatlinehu, even though you've nullified them, you stood up
and you made a declaration and you said 'I am making these
pillows and blankets part of my floor, they're going to remain here
for the whole week.' No, that doesn't matter, לכולו, le-kullu, some had
the גרסא girsah לכולהו, le-kulluhu, for the entire time. Why? משום דבטלה
דעתו אצל כל אדם, Mishum de-batla daato etzel kol adam, a very
important principle. Your intention is negated regarding that of the normal people.
Normal people don't leave pillows and blankets on the floor for a
week. But it actually is interesting because right, in some like Mid-Eastern
cultures, right, you have like pillows like all on the floor, they
basically do serve as like
your, you know, your basic like carpeting essentially and they don't really
get removed. But the גמרא Gemara is assuming I don't know maybe
it was a little bit different in a house that's out, you
know, that's especially if you have a dirt floor. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says that's not really, you really don't make them part of
the floor. Look רש"י Rashi says, if you take a look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the
bottom רש"י Rashi on ג עמוד ב, Gimmel Amud Bet, לא הוי
מיעוט שאין סופו להניח שם כל שבעה פני הפסד ממונו. lo hava
miut she-ein sofo le-haniach sham kol shiva p'nei hefsed mamono. That you're
not going to really, nobody expects a normal person to leave it
there for all seven. So that means that we don't really believe
or we don't treat as significant your desire because normal people don't
leave it there the whole week. One does wonder whether even if
you genuinely were going to and normal people did leave it there
the whole week, the point I'm making like if the culture is
to have pillows regularly to have like pillows on a floor and
covering the floor, that doesn't necessarily mean that they are part of
the floor, meaning you could have something there for an ongoing period
and intend to do that and that could be the culture, but
it doesn't mean that they get incorporated into and being seen as
the floor itself. They're always seen as distinct from the floor. They're
pillows on the floor, they're not the new floor. So but for
one way or another your intention does not signify because these either
we don't really have the status of being there for the week
or I would say further... Even if they are going to be
there for the week and that is the norm, they don't become
incorporated into the floor. Now this idea בטל דעתו אצל כל אדם
batel da’ato etzel kol adam is very important. How much does הלכה
Halacha care about your subjective intention? How much does it care about
the norms? And there are different הלכות Halachot about that, but very
often if your intention is it's sometimes willing to consider your intention
if it's off the chart of the norms to be maybe more
stringent but not necessarily to be more lenient. And it sort of
gets it has to get you know counterbalanced by what the norms
are in that case. A good example of that is the issue
of חציצה. chatzitza. Right, we say that if you're לא מקפיד lo
makpid on something on your body then it's not a חציצה. chatzitza.
Well let's say normal people are מקפיד makpid but you for some
crazy reason are not. Or let's say the opposite, normal people aren't
מקפיד makpid and you for some crazy reason are, right? So to
what degree do we look at what the norms are to determine
whether it counts as a חציצה, chatzitza, to what degree do we
look at what your intention is? So בטל דעתו אצל כל אדם
batel da’ato etzel kol adam is an important principle which is not
always applied but often applied to, not again if your if your
intention would make us more lenient and that goes against the norm
we might negate it and that's the idea that we look at
the normal intentions and the normal way people operate and not necessarily
you know weigh in favor of your subjective intention. Yes, though. Okay,
so that's number one, if you want to have the pillows there
for the whole week, it doesn't help, it doesn't it's not considered
raising the
floor. תבן וביטלו, teven u-vitlo, now let's say you have straw. Now
again remember they basically had dirt floors you know and you wanted
to put straw, well that's a normal type of a thing maybe
to actually become a type of a carpeting and actually become incorporated
into the floor. So if you intentionally are מבטל mevatel it, meaning
you say I am sort of making it part of the floor,
that's what מבטל mevatel means, you sort of negate it from its
independent identity and you and you sort of say that I'm intending
to leave it there and it's going to be part of the
floor. הוי מיעוט, havei miyut, that works, that does become
incorporated. וכל שכן עפר וביטלו, ve-chol sheken afar u-vitlo, and certainly if
you take dirt and you're מבטלו, mevatlo, again it's a dirt floor
to begin with, that becomes incorporated into the floor and that raises
the floor. Now how about some middle
cases? תבן ואין דעתו לפנותו, teven ve-ein da'ato lifnoto, if you have
straw that you're not like planning on removing it. In your mind
you never said oh let's make this part of the floor. On
the other hand you have no intentions of removing it. You know
it's there you haven't thought about it too much but you're certainly
or maybe you've explicitly said yeah I'm not going to bother to
take I'm not going to bother to take the straw out. But
you haven't like actively designated it as part of the floor. ועפר
סתם, ve-afar stam, or you have dirt there that you haven't even
thought about. You haven't decided you are taking it out you aren't
taking it out you haven't given it a second thought. So in
those cases right you understand why those are interesting middle cases because
dirt is very much objectively and naturally it's the same material as
the floor. So its just presence there could automatically define it as
part of the floor until maybe you actively want to remove it,
okay? Or maybe not, maybe dirt requires somehow that you you indicate
that you're not going to remove it. But you could understand how
its natural presence could make it part of the floor. Straw is
another middle case. Straw is not naturally incorporated into the floor but
it's a thing that's a reasonable thing to be part of the
floor. So in that case if you left it there סתם stam
without saying anything so okay maybe not, but let's say you consciously
have decided you're not going to remove it, that might be enough.
So how do you deal with those two cases? Is that clear
by the way? We have we have sort of like a chart
of you know of degree that you of your דעת. da'at. ביטלו
bitlo means you want it to be you intentionally say you want
it to be part of the floor. Okay the opposite of ביטלו
bitlo is עתיד לפנותו. atid lifnoto. You consciously are planning on removing
it, okay? Planning on remove it. The two things that are in
the middle of this of this continuum is the case about סתם,
stam, okay, which is you're just you have you're not thinking, no
plans, you know you're not thinking about it, it's just
there. ואין דעתו לפנותו, ve-ein da'ato lifnoto, which is you consciously are
you're planning to not remove it, planning to not remove, right? But
you haven't consciously made it part of the floor. Like you sort
of see how that's a continuum? Right? You are consciously planning on
removing, you're consciously planning on making it out of the floor, you're
not thinking about anything, you're consciously leaving it there but you're not
consciously making it part of the floor. So that's like your continuum.
Okay? So what it says is that if you have ביטלו bitlo
by עפר afar plus עפר afar and תבן, teven, that's like the
best of all worlds. You've got materials that are naturally part of
the floor plus your intention, that's part of the floor. If you
have it by by הכרים hakarim and כסתות, ksetot, right? So that
even ביטלו bitlo won't work, right? Even ביטלו bitlo won't help you.
But this, you have something that's naturally plus your intention, combination will
work. What about these things which your intention is in the some
middle range? What about that? Okay? And it says is that if
you have ביטלו bitlo by In that case, let's test it. So
עפר סתם, afar stam, which is the better material but the slightly
less better intention, or תבן ואינו עתיד לפנותו, teven ve-eino asid lifnoto,
the less ideal material to be part of the floor but the
better
intention, will those combinations work? Okay, is that sort of clear?
If you want, I just don't understand the difference between אינו עתיד
לפנותו eino asid lifnoto and part of the floor.
Part of the floor means you say, "I want this, this, I
brought in let's say this straw because I want to thicken my
floor. I want it to be part of my floor." As opposed
to, somebody dropped some straw on my ground, it fell off the
table, it's on the ground, eh, I'm just going to leave it
there, who cares? So it's not a big difference, but it's not
like a conscious making it part of the floor. Okay, is that...
yeah, it's not a huge difference.
Could you be מבטל mevatel something for just a certain period of
time?
Well, that's an interesting question. Let's say your ביטול bitul here is
for the... presumably, yes. For presumably for this week I want it
to serve as the floor of the סוכה, sukkah, okay? All right,
you know, a way to quantify this, which I'm not saying what
the גמרא gemara is doing, but a way to quantify this is
thinking of assigning a number to, you know, to like to materials
and a number to the intention, and what's the minimum combination of
the number? All right, forget it. Anyway, let's take a look. So
the גמרא gemara says like this, says that if you have the
combination of the
two, that is מחלוקת רב יוסי ורבנן, machloket Reb Yosei ve-rabbanan, the
debate of Reb Yosei and the Rabbis. דתנן, ditnan, we taught in
the משנה. mishna. Now this is a משנה mishna by אהלות, ohalot,
by the הלכות halachot that... by the way תוספות tosafot interestingly says
it's not really a משנה mishna by אהלות, ohalot, it's a paraphrase
and a sort of a you know like a rewriting of a
משנה mishna to get to the in order to make it more
accessible and relevant, which is interesting. Like תוספות tosafot points out how
what we're about to quote is not a text of a משנה,
mishna, but it's inferred from the משנה, mishna, and since the משנה
mishna was a lot more complicated, the גמרא gemara actually just rewrote
the משנה mishna in a way that was directly applicable here, which
is sometimes I feel I wish it would do that more often
like... but anyway, but anyway, okay, but this but what is the
idea? By אהלות, ohalot, the idea is is that if you have
טומאה, tumah, let's say a dead body, and it's under a roof,
then the טומאה tumah is considered to hit the roof and to
spread and it stays within the house. Okay, that's the טומאה tumah
of a corpse. However, if there's not a טפח tefach between the
floor and the roof, less than a טפח, tefach, then it's like
there's no roof and the טומאה tumah bursts through and goes straight
up. That's a problem like planes flying over cemeteries and so on.
Okay, that any... so it's not in the house, but it's anything
directly above the corpse is a problem. So let's say you've got
a טפח, tefach, but then what you do is you fill dirt
up in the gaps here. Does that... does that change the sense
of the gap between the floor and the roof? The same question
here, but here the issue is to determine whether you have a
טפח tefach gap. So let's take a look at what the משנה
mishna says. בית שמילאו תבן או צרורות. bayis she-milo'o teven o tzerorot.
A house, you actually had a corpse in a house, and you
fill the entire house with straw or with rocks. Rocks is effectively
the same as the as the dirt. וביטלו, u-vitlo, and you negated
it there. מבוטל, mevutal, it's nullified and it becomes part... and therefore
it's you no longer have an אהל ohel and it has all
those relevant הלכות. halachot. So that's ביטול bitul plus the straw and
the rocks. That's the easy case. So now the
גמרא gemara comments: ביטלו אין לא ביטלו לא. bitlo in, lo bitlo
lo. So according to the author of that משנה, mishna, only active
ביטול bitul plus the good materials works. Anything less than active ביטול
bitul would not work. דתניא עלה, detanya alah, but we have a
ברייתא braita on this. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbe Yosei omer, תבן ואינו
עתיד לפנותו, teven ve-eino asid lifnoto, הרי הוא כעפר סתם ובטל. harei
hu ke-afar stam u-vatel. If you have straw and you're planning to
not remove it, then that's equivalent to dirt that you're just... that
you have no intention. Those are two middle cases, and both of
those work, and they are בטל. batel. As long as you have
a really good material like dirt, then even no דעת da'at works,
and if you have a pretty good material like straw, then planning
on leaving it there, that also works, and you don't need active
דעת da'at to be מבטל. mevatel.
Kind of גילוי דעת, gilluy da'at, no?
No, it's defining the nature of the object based on the physical
reality of the floor and the object and how much they incorporate
into one another plus your intention.
Okay, you put soil on a soil floor, it's not an...
no, first of all, you didn't necessarily put it, your kid maybe
spilled it there. You didn't give it... you haven't even been thinking
about it, you're away at work, you don't even know it's there
yet. So it's not about a גילוי דעת, gilluy da'at, it's about
the combination of your דעת da'at and the reality and the physical
reality. Okay, that's the way I would understand it. Okay. Now, הרי
הוא כעפר... harei hu ke-afar... now, עפר ועתיד לפנותו... afar ve-asid lifnoto...
however, if the intentions are not as ideal, you have עפר, afar,
true, it's the better material, but it's higher up on the sort
of intention continuum, your plan is to remove it. הרי הוא כסתם
תבן, harei hu kistam teven, then that's equivalent to a case of
straw, a less ideal material, and no intention, also less ideal intention,
ולא בטל, ve-lo batel, and it is not
good. somewhat okay intention, or the second best material with a pretty
with a better intention. Those two are good. However, if you moved
them up, if you moved them up one, right, if you had
the עפר Afar and you were planning on removing it or the
תבן Teven and it had no intention, then it would not be
good. But in that case, they work. Okay, so that's seeing the
way in which you can raise the floor based on the material
and based on your intention. Now I want to say one thing
before we continue. You might notice that the structure of this גמרא
Gemara is a little strange. It doesn't start with quoting a ברייתא,
Beraita, it doesn't start with an אמורא Amora saying אמר רבי, Amar
Rabbi, you know, like אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, here's the
הלכה. Halakha. It's just the anonymous voice of the גמרא Gemara saying
a halakhic statement. Normally the anonymous voice is the one that's weaving
together the voices of the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים, Amoraim, or
maybe it's introducing a משנה Mishnah or a ברייתא Beraita in order
to then have the statements of the אמוראים, Amoraim, but it's not
usually like you don't normally have like the גמרא Gemara saying like
okay, in this case here's the הלכה, Halakha, in this case this
is the case, in this case... so what's going on here? So
if you take a look, it's an interesting רש"י. Rashi. Look at
the second רש"י Rashi from the bottom on ג עמוד ב. Gimmel
amud bet. רש"י Rashi says the following: היתה גבוהה מעשרים, Hayeta gevoha
me-esrim, says רש"י, Rashi, פסקי שמועות הן. Piskei shemu'ot hen. These are
like sort of, you know, פסקים, psakim, rulings of discussions, like bottom-line
conclusions. In current scholarly language, it might be somewhat apodictic, okay, as
opposed to discursive. שכל בני ישיבה שהיו במדרשו של רב אשי שסידרו
הגמרא. Shekol benei yeshivah shehayu be-midrasho shel Rav Ashi shesidro ha-gemara. So
רש"י Rashi attributes it to רב אשי Rav Ashi because for רש"י,
Rashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi is the sort of editor of the
גמרא. Gemara. You know, currently academically we sort of assign it, you
know, assume it to be later, but the point still is whoever
did the editing of the גמרא, Gemara, these were like traditions of
פסקים, psakim, and actually it is not the no-name אמורא, Amora, this
was like consensus and traditions of פסקים psakim that were passed down,
and that these were just presented in a much more apodictic type
of a form. Okay, so one was raising the floor. Now back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Now we're going to deal with other related
types of cases. Okay, היתה גבוהה עשרים אמות. Hayeta gevoha esrim ammot.
Now what we're going to... I'm sorry, I skipped down a line.
היתה גבוהה מעשרים אמה. Hayeta gevoha me-esrim ammah. Now it was higher
than twenty אמה. ammah. So again we've got a problem. But here's
how we might lower the height. והוציא נרדים בתוך כ'. Vehutzi neradim
betoch kaf. And you have like, you know, twigs and going, coming
in within twenty. So again you measure, it's clear from this you
measure to the bottom of the סכך. s'chach. Okay, so your gap
from the floor to the סכך s'chach is twenty אמה, ammah, but
now from the סכך s'chach you've got some twigs, you've got like
some, you know, some like extensions that are hanging within twenty. Is
that considered to be the new bottom of the סכך, s'chach, right?
So is that clear?
Draw my picture?
Here's your סוכה, succa, it's a really high סוכה, succa,
okay, there's your floor, okay, so you've got here, you've got your
twenty אמות ammot or, you know, or whatever, we'll call it twenty-one,
okay, that's your height, but then here's your סכך, s'chach, and then
you have is you have some stuff that's hanging down from the
סכך, s'chach, and if you were to measure from the bottom of
this, then it would only be twenty. Okay, so is that okay?
Do you go from where the main סכך s'chach is or do
you go from where the bottom hanging of the סכך? s'chach? Okay,
so אם צלתה מרובה מחמתה כשירה. im tzilto merubbah mechamatam kesherah. So
if the extended hang itself provides more shade than sunlight, so then
it is considered to be the סכך s'chach proper, because it by
itself could provide enough shade. ואם לאו פסולה. ve-im lav pesulah. But
if not, it doesn't count as סכך, s'chach, so the הלכה Halakha
is were you to remove this סכך s'chach and the stuff that's
now hanging and that gets to be within twenty, like if this
itself could provide sufficient shade, then you're good. But if actually it
itself is not providing sufficient shade, then you can't count it the
סכך. s'chach. Only this is the סכך s'chach and the סכך s'chach
is too high. All right?
A lot of stuff hanging down.
Well, I made it twenty and twenty-one. You could have made it
that it was that this height was twenty point one and it
only has to hang down point one. Okay, but the point is...
oh, you mean a lot of stuff in terms of the... right,
the actual distribution, not just a lot of length. Right, that is
correct.
Your picture book has that
as a...
okay, alright. So that's... so you need that stuff that gets to
within twenty to continue to be considered to be סכך. s'chach. Going
on. היתה גבוהה עשרה טפחים. Hayeta gevoha asarah tefachim. Now we're dealing
with maximum height, we're going to deal with minimum height. If it
was only עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high, והוציא נרדים בתוך עשרה. vehotzi
neradim betoch asarah.
Now we have a case where it's the reverse. You don't want
to lower the סכך. s'chach. It's ten טפחים tefachim high and the
stuff, the strands that are hanging down go within ten טפחים. tefachim.
So if you consider that to be סכך, s'chach, now it's too
small. So what's the הלכה? halacha? So סבר אביי למימר, savar Abaye
l'meimar, so אביי Abaye thought it was the same basic principle applied
in this case. אם חמתן מרובה מצלתן, im chamtzan meruba metzilatan, if
there's more sun than shade in that extended hang, so כשירה, kesheira,
it's kosher because then it doesn't count as סכך s'chach and otherwise
then obviously it would be too small of a height.
רבא Rava said, no, הדירה סרוחה היא, hadira s'rucha hi, that's a
smelly literally a habitation, habitat. אין אדם דר בדירה
סרוחה, ein adam dar b'dira s'rucha,
you cannot live in a smelly habitat. Now smelly is not technically
the point but it means like spoiled or whatever, it's uninhabitable is
basically what רבא Rava is saying. He's saying look, ten טפחים tefachim
already is pushing it. How are you supposed to live in a
place that's only like two feet high? So maybe you can if
you're always lying down, okay, but it's pushing it. But not only
that you can only lie down and you have your roof right
here, but you got little strands of סכך s'chach falling into your
face, that's uninhabitable. So technically it might be minimum height, I'm not
invalidating it because of the height issue, I'm invalidating it because it's
uninhabitable. תוספות Tosafot of course says and before otherwise it wasn't uninhabitable?
תוספות Tosafot says
what type of a place can you live in that you can't
stand up in? Meaning I've been explaining you don't have to sit
up to eat, you can recline to eat, but תוספות Tosafot says
what type of a habitation is it that you can't stand up
straight in? Anyway, this makes it completely uninhabitable. All right, הייתה גבוהה
מעשרים אמה, hayta gevoha m'esrim ama, back to being too high, was
higher than twenty אמות. amot. ובנה בה אצטבא, ubana ba itztaba,
now you built a platform, כנגד דופן האמצעי, kineged dofen ha-emtza'i, opposite
the the middle wall. If you take a look actually got nice
little picture in the גמרא Gemara itself, and basically normally the גמרא
Gemara assumes that a סוכה sukkah has three walls, doesn't assume four
walls. So you've got three walls and you built this platform opposite
the like along the length of the middle wall. So if you
think about it, if that platform above that platform the platform is
high enough that above that platform is let you know you've raised
the floor is less than twenty אמות. amot. So right, so that
area around the platform is the right height. And that area around
the platform has three walls, right, the half of the left and
the right wall and all of the back wall. So that area
above the אצטבא itztaba itself is a kosher סוכה. sukkah.
This is an aerial view. This is an aerial view, okay. Is
it I think the picture is pretty clear, right? ובנה בה ubana
ba
על פני כולה, al p'nei kula, the length of the entire opposite
wall, ויש בה הכשר סוכה, veyesh ba hachshar sukkah,
and the area above the platform is the minimum size of a
סוכה, sukkah, so then you've got a סוכה sukkah there. The whole
area of the platform is surrounded by three walls and it's and
it's not too high, it's perfect. כשירה, kesheira, it is kosher. Okay,
so that's clear, right, why that works? That's a pretty straightforward case.
רש״י Rashi by the way makes a חידוש chiddush that not only
is the platform kosher but the rest of the סוכה sukkah is
also kosher. And this becomes an interesting question which is if you
have a part of the סוכה sukkah that's kosher, do you see
the rest of the סוכה sukkah as somehow just an adjunct to
the part that's kosher? Now normally we would say no if the
problem is the סכך, s'chach, like imagine that I have a little
strip of kosher סכך s'chach and the rest is covered with metal
bars. Would I say oh well I can sit under the metal
bars because this piece of the סוכה sukkah is kosher? The answer
would be no. Normally we say it when the problem is the
walls. Let's say I've got a kosher סוכה sukkah here and then
the סכך s'chach extends outwards but the walls don't follow the סכך.
s'chach. So and I sit under the סכך, s'chach, so I'm sitting
under kosher סכך, s'chach, it doesn't have walls, there we would say
okay but I'm under kosher סכך s'chach and it's part of that
סוכה sukkah over there that has walls, that's okay. That would be
a normal scenario where we could say you could sit in the
non-kosher part and you're considered part of the kosher part when you
have kosher סכך s'chach but you don't have walls. That's the case
the גמרא Gemara deals with. רש״י Rashi applies that here, which is
interesting because it raises the question is the too high סכך s'chach
is the too high סוכה sukkah a problem of the סכך s'chach
or a problem of the wall? If it's a problem of the
walls, then you could say even in the other part of the
סוכה sukkah that's not the platform I'm under kosher סכך, s'chach, I'm
just not in the walls of the סוכה sukkah but that's okay,
I'm an extension, I'm a connect- right, that seems to be how
רש״י Rashi is saying it, but the alternative is to say the
סכך s'chach is invalid and then the rest of the סוכה sukkah
wouldn't be kosher. So I don't know if I just lost everybody
there but I want you to appreciate what- but
you're not connected, you're at a different level.
Yeah, but it's all the extension of the same walls and the
extension of the same סכך. s'chach. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara here says
that it's kosher, רש״י Rashi adds the חידוש chiddush that not only
is on top of the platform... from רש״י Rashi but even the
extension is כשר kosher and all I'm telling you is that's not
so פשוט pashut and it might depend on whether it's you see
the problem being in the walls or the problem being in the
סכך. s'chach. Okay, so that's that case. Now, how about ומן הצד?
u-min ha-tzad? Let's say you built your platform lengthwise of the סוכה.
sukkah. Again, look at that picture and so that picture you can
see you only have two exterior walls, correct? The thing going down
in the middle isn't a wall, the thing going down in the
middle is the platform is the edge of the platform. So in
that case you only have two exterior walls, right? You've got a
problem. So what do you do? אם יש משפת האצטבא לכותל ארבע
אמות, im yesh mi-sefat ha-itztaba le-kotel arba amot, פסולה. pesulah.
If there's four אמות amot separating the platform and the far wall,
then it's invalid because you only have two walls. פחות מארבע אמות,
pachot me-arba amot, כשרה kesherah but less than four אמות amot is
valid. Why? So this is a principle, one of the important principles
we're going to learn in סוכה sukkah called
דופן
עקומה.
dofen
akumah. דופן dofen means wall and עקומה akumah means bent, okay? Or
I basically translate as the magic bending wall. Okay, so there's going
to be a lot of magic here, okay? Now, how does the
magic bending wall work? The way the magic bending wall works is
let's say you've got a house where you've got your permanent, your
permanent, well maybe that looks like סכך. s'chach. Anyway, you've got your
permanent roof here, okay? That's your roof, you've got your house, and
we're going to have this case in a minute. But then a
section of your roof falls in, okay? And you say oh a
section's fallen in, perfect! What I'm going to do is I'm going
to fill it with סכך, s'chach,
okay? I'm going to fill it with סכך s'chach and I'm going
to make the area underneath my כשר סוכה. kasher Sukkah, There's only
a bit of a problem which is the area directly underneath has
no walls adjacent to it, right? The walls are distant. So the
principle of the magic bending wall says if this, if the distance
from the סכך s'chach to the real wall is less than four
אמות, amot, then we can say that this סכך s'chach isn't סכך,
s'chach, I mean not the סכך, s'chach, this roof isn't roof. This
roof is actually just a bent wall. And therefore what the roof
here is, is it's actually, I mean actually you've got one bent
wall going that way and if this is less than four אמות
amot you've got another bent wall going that way and I think
you get the idea, right? And if these things are considered to
be bent walls, the roof is a bent wall, so then this
space in the middle if that's less than four אמות amot you
can look at the roof as a bent wall and say they
all it has adjacent walls. Is that pretty clear what we're saying?
That's impressive that you could draw that.
Thank you. Anyway, so what the גמרא Gemara is saying in this
case is if you've got here your סוכה, sukkah. which is way,
which is too high, but you've got your platform, okay? And your
platform makes it, this is the here, this is your, this is
less than 20 אמות, amot, that's your platform, but you've only got
two walls, there's no wall here. You've only got two walls. It
says no problem because if from here to here is less than
four
אמות, amot, then this, then this wall, right, this wall is higher
than is higher than 20, whatever, this wall here, which is too
far away, right, but you've also, you have סכך, s'chach, the only
problem was that it was higher than 20, right? So this wall
bends all the way here if this distance is less than four
and therefore this actually will have three walls. All right?
And does it bend over the top or actually the way I
read it is that this is not just a bent magic bending
wall, it's a magic bending wall that can be invisible. Oh no.
It's, the
סכך s'chach doesn't even have to touch the wall for the bending
wall.
We will get to invisible later but now let's assume everything touches
and we're just bending it, okay? We'll deal later with the fact
that you also have, that's the other magic. And then there's a
question if you can combine two magic principles, okay? About six feet.
Six feet? Right. So if the point here to here is the
white space, which is higher than 20, if that white space, the
distance from the edge to the other opposite wall is less than
four, then you use the סכך s'chach on top of that white
space to pull the wall, to extend the wall so it's touching,
so it's connected to the סכך s'chach above the platform. Okay, so
that's the principle. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן? mai
ka-mashma lan? What are you, what are you teaching me? דאמרינן דופן
עקומה? d'amrinan dofen akumah? That we say a principle of a bent
wall? תנינא! tenina! We taught it! בית שנפחת וסיכך על גביו, bayit
she-nifchat ve-sikach al gabav, as a house has the case I gave
you, it, the roof, a middle part of the roof fell in
and you put סכך s'chach in the middle of the, in that,
in that part that fell in. אם יש מן הכותל לסיכוך ארבע
אמות, im yesh min ha-kotel le-sikuch arba amot, פסולה. pesulah.
If there's the distance from the actual wall to the סכך s'chach
part is four אמות amot or more, it's invalid. הא פחות מכאן,
ha pachot mi-kan, implicitly it's telling you that less than that כשרה,
kesherah, it's כשר. kosher So you do this bending wall by the
סכך s'chach in the middle of your roof, so of course you
would do the bending wall by the So here with the platform
and to get the wall to be considered connected. The גמרא Gemara
says no. מהו דתימא אימא אצטריך התם הוא דחזי לדופן, Mah d'teima
eima itztarich hatam hu dechazi l'dofen,
there the wall is the right height, it's just not close enough.
But like if you've got the wall and the middle of your
roof fell in, the walls are good walls, halachic walls for a
סוכה. sukkah, They're just not close enough to the area of the
סכך. s'chach. So we bend the roof to bring them close to
the סכך. s'chach. But here in this case, this wall, there's no
platform in this section. This wall is a twenty-one אמה amah wall.
You might say this wall doesn't count by wall. By bending it,
we're not only bringing it close to the כשר kosher. סוכה, Sukkah.
we're redefining it as the right height wall. Right? If it gets
bent and placed here, its height would be defined from the top
of the platform. Right? Over here it's a twenty-one אמה amah wall.
After we've bent it and effectively moved it here, not only have
we made it join to the סוכה, Sukkah, but we actually have
now made it into a right-sized wall. So maybe you're not allowed
to do that. Maybe you have to start with the proper-sized wall.
התם הוא דחזי לדופן, Hatam hu dechazi l'dofen, there it's fit for
being a wall, it's only
it's just too far away from the middle, from the סכך s'chach
in the middle of your roof. אבל הכא דלא חזי לדופן, Aval
hacha d'lo chazi l'dofen, here where it is, it's not fit for
a wall. It's twenty-one אמות, amot, it's too high. אימא לא, Eima
lo, I might think that you can't bend it, which means both
effectively bringing it close and making it the right height. קמשמע לן
Kamashma lan that that's okay, you can do it, and as long
as it's within ארבע אמות, arba amot, you can see it as
juxtaposed, you can see it as contiguous, and therefore it's also transformed,
now its height has shrunk because now it's next to a platform,
so its effective height is
less.
Yes. So, within the right amount of space, distance, what's the difference
between דופן עקומה dofen akumah and גוד אסיק? gud asik?
So that's that's what the point about the invisible. גוד אסיק Gud
asik is you have a wall that's not high enough, and but
once it's ten טפחים tefachim high, it's imagined to continue to go
up straight. That's the other magic.
So I might as well put it there. There's a couple, but
the two major ones are דופן עקומה dofen akumah and גוד אסיק
מחיצתא. gud asik mechitzta. גוד Gud or גוד אסיק gud asik means
the wall goes up, sometimes it's גוד אסיק מחיצתא, gud asik mechitzta,
but anyway, means גוד gud is the wall, אסיק asik goes up,
which means if you start with a ten טפח tefach wall
and
you've got your סכך s'chach up here, right, and it's not touching
at the vertical plane, right, as opposed to not touching because at
the horizontal, so then the wall is continued to extend straight up.
Okay, so this is sort of, you know, the magic... So can
you do
both? Can you have both? So no, that's combining magic, that's what
I said, right?
This
is the magic invisible wall, or just the invisible wall. It's like
if you find a way
to
split it.
So this is, this is getting the walls close at the horizontal.
This is at the horizontal, combined, it's all about combining the walls,
combining the walls to the סכך, s'chach, right? This is combining them
on the horizontal plane and this is combining them on the vertical
plane. Okay, in both cases, the problem is that the walls don't
touch the סכך. s'chach. Only this is the vertical and this is
the horizontal and you're bringing them close on those different planes. Okay.
Whenever I talk about this, I always remember that scene from
Spaceballs where, you remember that, they're all running and they bump into
and they like, you know, bang into something that's like, you know,
you can't see, and they say, "What is this?" He says, "Oh,
that's an invisible wall." "Oh, that's an invisible wall? I always wanted
to know what an invisible wall looks like." So anyway, okay. Can
either of
these be פסול? pasul? What? Yeah, that's the... yeah, we'll worry about
all of that. All right. So the ברייתא braita says like this.
Okay. Now, היתה גבוהה מעשרים אמה, Haitah g'vohah m'esrim amah, it was
higher than twenty אמות, amot, ובנה
איצטבא באמצעיתה,
uvanah
itztava b'emtza'itah, you built a platform in
the middle. Now it's really like the case of the סכך s'chach
in the middle of the roof. So you have to bend all
four walls or all three
walls. אם יש משפת איצטבא ולדופן ארבע אמות לכל רוח ורוח פסולה,
Im yesh mis'fat itztava u'l'dofen arba amot l'chol ruach v'ruach psulah, if
the distance from the platform to the walls is ארבע אמות, arba
amot, then you can't bend them. It's invalid. פחות מארבע אמות, Pachot
m'arba amot, however, if it's within ארבע אמות arba amot of three
of the walls, like you need the three walls, so if the
distance between it and, you know, three separate walls in three separate
directions is less than ארבע אמות, arba amot, then כשרה, kasherah, then
you bend those three walls and you have the walls juxtaposed, you
know, or contiguous with the סכך. s'chach. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what are you telling me? דאמרינן
דופן עקומה, d'amrinan dofen akumah, that we bend walls? היינו הך, Hainu
hach, it's what you just said. No, says, מהו דתימא, mah d'teima,
I might have thought דופן עקומה מרוח אחת אמרינן, dofen akumah meruach
achat amrinan, you can say one wall you can bend, אבל לכל
רוח ורוח לא, aval l'chol ruach v'ruach lo, maybe you can't bend
it for all three walls, all three directions, קמשמע לן kamashma lan
that yes, you can. can do it on multiple walls. Okay, הייתה,
hayta, now we get to not maximum height but minimum height.
Rabbi, I'm sorry, so does that mean if you've got like a
patch of סכך sechach in the middle, open air on all four
sides?
No, no, good question. To bend the wall, you need real סכך.
sechach. Meaning what allows you to bend the wall is that the
סכך, sechach, the physical material of the סכך, sechach, is considered to
be part of the physical wall.
And
that was your question about doing it with like the invisible things?
You can't. Okay, you need to actually need physical material to bend
and it allows you to envision the roof as part of the
wall, but you actually need the physical matter.
You can't imagine the stuff also.
Right, right, exactly. Okay. הייתה פחותה מעשרה טפחים. hayta pechuta me'asara tefachim.
Okay, so it's less than ten טפחים, tefachim, too small. וחקק בה
כדי להשלימה לעשרה. ve'chakak bah kedei le'hashlima le'asara.
And now what you are doing is you are going to dig
into the floor in order to get, you know, you're going to
lower the floor, okay? So you dig a hole. אם יש משפת
החקק—now im yesh mi'sefat ha'chakak here's the problem.
The problem is that
the problem is now we get to introduce לבוד. lavud. Okay, here's
your סוכה, sukka, okay, it's very short. Okay, this is nine טפחים
tefachim and what you did was here in the ground, let's move
that, here in the ground in the middle, this is sort of
like the reverse of, you know, right here in the middle of
the ground, you dug a hole.
Okay,
so you've got now from the floor here, from the floor of
your hole to the top you've got ten טפחים. tefachim. But you've
got a problem. What's your problem? That that kosher סוכה sukka is
like is not touching the wall. Again, you dug your hole in
the middle, right? So right here is the minimum height, right? But
the walls are distant. So what would you say you would need
in order to get the walls to be considered adjacent? Less than
four אמות. amot. So you think less than four אמות. amot. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. It seems like we're getting ready
to say the same thing, but if from the edge of the
pit, of the pit, of the—if it's וכותל ג' טפחים u'lakosel gimel
tefachim פסולה, psula, it's invalid. פחות משלושה טפחים כשרה. pachot mi'shlosha tefachim
kshira.
I'm sorry, if it's three טפחים tefachim or more it's invalid, less
than three טפחים tefachim it is כשר. kasher. So now the גמרא
Gemara asks the obvious question. By the way, you'll notice not one
תנא tanna nor one אמורא amora has, you know, it's completely the
anonymous voice of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. The only תנא tanna was
mentioned was when it brought in a משנה. mishna. מאי שנא התם
דאמרת פחות מארבע אמות? mai shna hatam de'amrat pachot me'arba amot? Why,
when you've got a section in the middle that's too high, you
say less than four אמות, amot, you know, up to four אמות
amot you can bend in the wall. ומאי שנא הכא דאמרת פחות
משלושה טפחים? u'mai shna hacha de'amrat pachot mi'shlosha tefachim?
And why here does it have to be three טפחים, tefachim, which
is radically less, right? It's about what is that? Five inches or
so. And the other is like six feet. The גמרא Gemara says
no. התם דאית ליה דופן, hatam de'is lei dofen, there you start
with the wall. פחות מארבע אמות סגי pachot me'arba amot sagi because
you can continue to bend the wall. הכא לשוויה דופן, hacha leshavei
dofen,
you don't have a wall yet. Less than ten טפחים tefachim is
not only invalid as a סוכה. sukka. Less than ten טפחים tefachim
is also the minimum height for what? A halachic wall, a מחיצה
mechitza for a wall for like רשות היחיד reshut ha'yachid on שבת,
Shabbat, other areas you need a wall. So if it starts with
this thing, if these walls are only nine טפחים tefachim high, you
can't bend them to get them here, they're not yet halachically a
wall. The same way when you have the magic rising wall, it's
only once that wall is ten טפחים tefachim can you imagine it
to go up. You need to start with a wall. So if
you start with a wall but it's twenty-one אמות, amot, you can
bend it. But here it's only nine טפחים, tefachim, so therefore you
can't bend that wall. So you can't have the principle of the
magic bending wall. What principle do you have? You have a principle
of לבוד. lavud. If that's less than three טפחים, tefachim, לבוד lavud
is a principle that without any bending, things are just considered to
be contiguous if they're within three טפחים tefachim of one another. Okay?
So that's why if it's less than three then it literally is
like it's right up against the wall. I mean, let me give
you an example, right? Let's say it was a centimeter removed, right?
Would you say, well, you don't have a wall, ten טפחים, tefachim,
because it's a centimeter off? You know, we say no, that's effectively
it's the same thing, it's like it's connected. So לבוד lavud is
a little bit more than a centimeter, five inches, but it means
within three טפחים tefachim it's considered like it's all right next to
each other. And that you don't need it to have a status
of a wall. You're not saying a bending wall. Any two things
that were within three טפחים tefachim are like they're connected to one
another.
עשרה טפחים asara tefachim is about three feet, is
about yeah, thirty inches, about three
or
three feet, something like that. Okay. Okay, so הכא לשוויה דופן, hacha
leshavei dofen, here you're turning it into a wall, you're trying to
get the minimum ten טפחים. tefachim. פחות משלושה טפחים אין, pachot mi'shlosha
tefachim in, less than three טפחים tefachim yes, אי לאו. ei lo.
no, if not, not. Now, I want to say two things at
this stage. First of all, what does the word לבוד lavud mean?
I mean, I think effectively, like I said, it means that it's
considered contiguous. But if you look at the רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi
says the following, רש״י Rashi says second line from the top, לבוד
lavud says רש״י Rashi in the middle of the line, סניף, snif,
it's an appendage, an extension, אפותיסטא, apotista, whatever that is. דבר שמאריכין
אותו על ידי סניפין. davar shema'arichin oto al yedei snifin.
Think about like your table when you put in a, you know,
an extension into your table, a leaf, right? So כדסניף חקק על
חקק. kedasnif chakak al chakak.
It's like you extended a ditch onto your ditch. So basically you're
allowed to like extend a thing up to three טפחים. tephachim. That's
the way רש״י Rashi says the word לבוד lavud itself means an...
it's a virtual extension of the thing that you're dealing with so
that up to three טפחים tephachim it's considered to extend and therefore
make them to actually be contiguous. But that's the idea of לבוד
lavud within three טפחים tephachim is contiguous. Now, I want to say
another interesting point which is that תוספות Tosafot says we don't say
this by שבת. Shabbat. By שבת Shabbat there's an exact similar case
and it says that if you dig a hole here in the
middle of your whatever and there's walls... let's not make it a...
whatever and there's let's say whatever and you dig your little hole
and it's, you know, whatever, you know, five טפחים tephachim and there's
a wall here, you know, there's walls around it that are only
five טפחים. tephachim. Okay. So that inside this hole by שבת Shabbos
is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay, so it's the same idea,
right, five טפחים tephachim plus five טפחים tephachim make ten טפחים. tephachim.
But תוספות Tosafot says but we don't need it to be within
three טפחים tephachim of the walls. Why not? What's the difference? How
come for שבת Shabbos it's רשות היחיד reshut hayachid even though I
mean
you need three directions
but anyway how come by שבת Shabbos it's רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
even if it's not contiguous to the walls and here it isn't?
And תוספות Tosafot says a very important point. He says by שבת
Shabbos by... you don't need the idea of a house. By סוכה
Sukkah you need the idea of a house. So a house, the
walls are contiguous with the living space. So that's right? Is that
clear? So therefore you need it to be contiguous whereas by שבת
Shabbos the idea is if this is a zone that is sort
of separated off, protected from the outside... you know what does a
מחיצה mechitzah do? מחיצה mechitzah blocks traffic, right? So even if the
מחיצה, mechitzah, the blocking of the traffic occurs distant, but this zone
in the middle is a protected zone, that makes it a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. It doesn't need walls contiguous. It's not a structure
with walls. The idea of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid is a protected
zone. So the walls that actually protect can be distant from the
space itself that is designated as a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay,
so I just thought that was very interesting because although they're very
similar walls, ten טפחים tephachim and so on, there's a difference. A
סוכה Sukkah has a roof and a סוכה Sukkah is more of
a whole structure, the walls are part of the structure whereas by
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid the walls more protect the space in the
middle. Okay, let's keep on going.
Yeah, רשות reshut is a more abstract concept. That's true.
Not a dwelling
place.
Right, exactly. Exactly. It's not a dwelling place, it's abstract and therefore
the walls don't have to be an integral part of it. היתה
גבוהה מעשרים אמה. hayetah gevohah me'esrim amah. Now, it's higher than twenty
אמות. amot. ובנה בה עמוד שהוא גבוה עשרה טפחים. uvanah bah amud
shehu gavoha asarah tephachim.
Now you built in the middle a platform higher than ten טפחים.
tephachim. Now we're not going to be able to bend the wall.
Okay. But we're going to try to do something because let's say
it's way too big to bend the walls and your platform is
in the middle. But we're going to do something else. ויש בו
הכשר סוכה veyesh bo hechsher sukkah and on this platform is the
minimum size of a סוכה. sukkah. סבר אביי למימר savar Abaye lemeimar
and here becomes the other magic principle: גוד אסיק מחיצתא. gud asik
mechitzta. The wall extends up, the מחיצה mechitzah of the wall extends
up. So you got the case, meaning now what you've got is
the same idea of a platform in the middle but with one
new thing added. The size of the platform... here's you standing on
the platform... the size of the platform is ten טפחים. tephachim. Okay.
And you've got way here you've got your סכך sechach and it's
too
high. Okay. And this is way too far away from the walls,
it's five אמות amot away from the walls so you're not going
to be able to bend. Okay. But from here to the top
is good. So what אביי Abaye said is, hey, let's extend the
walls! The magic extending wall! Since the platform is ten טפחים, tephachim,
the outer wall of the platform, even though it doesn't have an
interior part, right, but just the outer face of the platform can
be a wall that extends up and therefore you could be okay.
So we got somebody shaking his head no. Let's see... רבא Rava
doesn't like it either. Let's see what רבא Rava says. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה רבא. amar leh Rava.
רבא Rava says בעינן מחיצות הניכרות וליכא. beinan mechitzot hanikarot veleika. No,
you need walls that are obviously walls. Now, why are these not
obviously
walls?
Because it's a platform.
Well, oh, so right, you could say two things: you could say
because they're invisible, okay, or you could say... and that raises question
when do we ever say גוד אסיק? gud asik? Or you could
say, no, because when you look at it, it's like it's, you
know, there's nothing, right, it's only like a wall on one side,
it has no interior and something like this, which is the face
of something, is not really a wall. All right, so let's take
a look how this plays out.
Well, but it's a foundation.
Yes, and
it is something.
Right,
it doesn't start also at your level. You don't see it. So
we're going to test what ניכרות nikarot means by the next case.
Let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabanan, we taught: נעץ קנה, נעץ ארבעה קונדסין וסיכך על גבן,
Na'atz kaneh, na'atz arba'ah kundasin vesichech al gaban,
you made four posts on your rooftop and you put סכך sechach
on them. So you're on your roof, and there are four posts,
and you put סכך sechach from post to post, you know, covering
the whole thing, but there's absolutely no walls. רבי יעקב מכשיר, Rabbi
Yaakov machshir, רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says it's כשר, kosher, וחכמים פוסלין,
vechachamim poslin, and the חכמים Chachamim say it's invalid. Now, let's take
a look. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מחלוקת על שפת הגג,
machloket al sefat hagag, the debate is at the edge of the
roof. דרבי יעקב סבר אמרינן גוד אסיק מחיצתא, DeRabbi Yaakov savar amrinan
gud asik mechitzta, the wall goes up, רבנן סברי לא אמרינן גוד
אסיק מחיצתא, Rabanan savri lo amrinan gud asik mechitzta, the wall doesn't
come up.
So that's a very similar scenario, right, which is here you are,
you're on your rooftop, this
is your Manhattan apartment building or whatever, you're on your roof, you
make these posts,
right, and you put סכך sechach on it. So רבי יעקב Rabbi
Yaakov says the wall goes up, the wall of the building goes
up. Okay, now, this is this the same case as the platform?
Right,
if you say this is good, will this be good? This is
a little bit better. Why is it better?
Because
these are real walls, these have an interior, right? You, they're invisible
to you on the top, but they are ניכרות, nikarot, not to
you on the top, there they're totally invisible, but they're ניכרות nikarot
because it's not just the face of something, there actually is a
wall, there actually is an interior to this. So that's how we're
going to test what is this idea of מחיצות הניכרות. mechitzot hanikarot.
Okay, but that's this case of will we extend the walls of
the apartment building? Yes.
What about the requirement to put fence around the top of the
roof?
Oh let's not worry about that. Okay, it's not your building, you
don't have that requirement, I don't know. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, good question. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so he says the debate is at the edge of the
building. אבל באמצע הגג דברי הכל פסולה, Aval be'emtza hagag divrei hakol
pesulah, if the posts were in the middle of the roof, obviously
it would be invalid. How could anybody say you have a wall?
So according to this the חכמים Chachamim would say that even to
use the edge of the building to say the extending wall
you would not say. ורב נחמן אמר, VeRav Nachman amar, ורב נחמן
veRav Nachman says, באמצע הגג מחלוקת. be'emtza hagag machloket. No, they debate
in the middle of the roof, because they, now if it's middle
of the roof, how could רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov say it's good?
We'll get to that in a minute. But what he's saying is
if it's at the edge of the roof, everybody would say you
could extend the wall. So the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, iba'ya
lehu, they raise the question according to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, באמצע
הגג מחלוקת, be'emtza hagag machloket, is it only the debate is in
the middle of the roof, אבל אשפת הגג דברי הכל כשרה, aval
asfat hagag divrei hakol kesherah, but by the edge of the roof
everybody would say it's good, everybody would extend the wall? או דילמא,
O dilma, or do we say בין בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת, bein
bezo uvein bezo machloket, that they actually debate both
cases? That the חכמים Chachamim would say not only the middle of
the roof is no good for obvious reasons, but even the edge
of the roof we won't extend the wall. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. But basically what you have here
is that according to one opinion they're debating the edge of the
roof and even there the חכמים Chachamim say you don't extend the
wall, so even that is not enough ניכרות nikarot because it's not
ניכר nikar to the people because it's not ניכר nikar to the
guy standing up here. According to the other version maybe they debate
the middle of the roof and maybe only the middle of the
roof, and maybe the edge of the roof everybody would agree is
okay and would say that this is better than this case. Here
at least the walls are evident below, here the walls are not
really evident to anyone. Okay, so what exactly is the parameters of
evident, evident to you or evident to anyone is part of what's
going on here.
But you're saying when it's in the middle of the roof, you
cannot apply both גוד אסיק gud asik and גוד אחית? gud achit?
Correct, absolutely.
That would solve the problem.
Yeah, yeah, okay, okay, exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, מיתיבי, Meitivei, now we're
not done, I'll ask. נעץ ארבעה קונדסין בארץ וסיכך על גבן, Na'atz
arba'ah kundasin ba'aretz vesichech al gaban, you put four posts on the
ground
and put סכך sechach on
them. רבי יעקב מכשיר וחכמים פוסלין. Rabbi Yaakov machshir vechachamim poslin. So
the
גמרא Gemara says והארץ כבאמצע הגג דמי, veha'aretz keve'emtza hagag dami, it's
like the middle of the roof, right? I mean there's no way
to use any extending walls, and nevertheless רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says
that even four posts with no extending walls is still
כשר. kasher. וקמכשיר רבי יעקב, Vekamachshir Rabbi Yaakov, and רבי יעקב Rabbi
Yaakov says it's כשר. kasher. So you see
that in the middle of the roof רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov is
willing to still say it's כשר, kasher, they're not just debating the
edge of the roof. תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא. Tiyuvta deRav Huna tiyuvta.
Okay, that's a contradiction to רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav
Huna said they're only debating the edge, nobody would say it's כשר
kasher in the middle. Here we see it's not true, we see
that רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says even without the extending wall it's
כשר. kasher. כשר. kosher. ועוד באמצע הוא דפליגי. Ve'od ba'emtza hu d'pligi.
Now the גמרא Gemara wants to push its case even more. Maybe
I'll say they're only debating the middle of the roof. They're only
debating this case of like being on the ground, אבל על שפת
הגג דברי הכל כשרה. Aval al sfat hagag divrei hakol keshera. Maybe
I should infer that by the edge of the roof, maybe everybody
would say it's okay, that you can say the extending wall. לימא
תהוי תיובתא דרב הונא בתרתי? Leima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav Huna bitartei?
Maybe this contradicts רב הונא Rav Huna in two ways? A, that
רב יעקב Rav Yaakov says it's good at the, you know, even
in the middle and רב הונא Rav Huna denied that. And the
second way is that רב יעקב Rav Yaakov maybe agrees that the
edge of... I mean the חכמים Chachamim agree that the edge of
the roof is good, and that was also being denied. So אמר
לך רב הונא, Amar lach Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna
would tell you no. פליגי באמצא גג והוא הדין על שפת הגג.
Pligi be'emtza gag vehu hadin al sfat hagag. Just because they debate
the middle of the roof, the case of the ground, does not
mean that they don't also debate the edge of the roof. והא
דקמיפלגי באמצא גג, Veha d'kamiflagi be'emtza gag, why are they discussing the
middle of the roof? להודיעך כוחו דרב יעקב, L'hodiecha kocho d'Rav Yaakov,
to tell you the חידוש chidush of רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, דאפילו
באמצא גג נמי מכשר, d'afilu be'emtza gag nami machshir,
that he says it's fine even in the middle of the roof.
Which means what? That we see that they debate the case of
the ground. We see that רב יעקב Rav Yaakov says that even
without extending walls it's okay. The חכמים Chachamim say it's no good.
Okay. Now, first of all, I should say a word about why...
no, you know what, we'll say in a minute the logic of
רב יעקב. Rav Yaakov. Okay, we'll get to that in a minute,
but you see they debate on the ground. So that רב יעקב
Rav Yaakov has a very bizarre position, it's okay, a very logical
חכמים Chachamim say it's no good. What about when it's at the
edge of the roof? Clearly, of course רב יעקב Rav Yaakov is
going to continue to say it's okay. Would the חכמים Chachamim there
say it's good or not? That's not clear. Maybe they would say
it's good. Okay, maybe they would say the extending wall. Maybe they'd
say it's no good. But the reason we're focusing on the case
of the middle of the roof is because it tells you the
tremendous חידוש chidush of רב יעקב. Rav Yaakov. That even without any
extending walls, he's going to make this כשר. kosher. Okay, the חכמים
Chachamim who disagree might also not even like the edge of the
roof, that we don't know. But we do know that רב יעקב
Rav Yaakov goes so far to say without any walls, just four
posts, it's going to be fine. And let's figure out why, and
that's the last piece. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: נעץ ארבעה קונדסין בארץ,
Na'atz arba'ah kundasin ba'aretz,
four posts in the ground, וסיכך על גביהן, vesichach al gabeihen, and
put סכך sechach on them. רב יעקב אומר: Rav Yaakov omer: רואין.
Ro'in. Now here's the explanation of רב יעקב. Rav Yaakov. כל שאילו
יחקקו, Kol she'ilu yechakiku,
if those poles are big enough that you could carve them, ויחלוקו,
veyachaloku, and split them, ויש בהן טפח לכאן וטפח לכאן, veyesh bahen
tefach l'chan v'tefach l'chan,
and there's a טפח tefach in each direction, נידונים משום דיומד. nidonim
mishum dyomed. They have a status of a דיומד, dyomed, which means
like a corner. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, אין נידונים משום דיומד, ein
nidonim mishum dyomed, and if not, they don't count as a corner.
שהיה רב יעקב אומר, Shehayah Rav Yaakov omer, דיומדי סוכה טפח, dyomdei
sukkah tefach,
that the corners of a סוכה sukkah are a טפח. tefach. וחכמים
אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, עד שיהו שתים כהלכתן ושלישית אפילו טפח, ad sheyehu
shtayim k'hilchatan v'shlishit afilu tefach, which means you need two full walls,
the last one can be a טפח. tefach. Which means what? Which
means that
if you have four posts, right? This is now an aerial view.
You've got four posts, but they're big enough that you can cut
out a square of a טפח tefach of a טפח. tefach. And
then from that square of a טפח tefach of a טפח, tefach,
you could actually imagine hollowing it out. So effectively they are big
enough that you can create four corners, each one a טפח tefach
by a טפח. tefach. Then he says that creates a structure, a
frame of four walls. And that frame of four walls, although you
don't actually have the physical wall, is enough to be כשר kosher
for a סוכה. sukkah. That's called a דיומד. dyomed. Now, by the
way, people who remember עירובין Eruvin might remember the case of פסי
ביראות, passei bira'ot, that you have a well in the middle and
you've got corners. There the corners have to be an אמה amah
long. Here it's a smaller structure, a טפח tefach is enough. So
he says if it's this, it would be כשר. kosher. And therefore,
even if you don't have the corners, even if it's just posts,
if they could in theory become those corners, that would be fine.
So you have to... you can, according to him, imagine the corners,
and from that, then imagine the walls. Exactly.
And the... so it's a double חידוש. chidush. And the חכמים Chachamim
say even if you have the corners, it wouldn't be good. You
need two and a half real walls. Okay, but the upshot of
all of this is, A, we've got a huge חידוש chidush here
about the דיומדין, dyomdin, but we have the principle about the גוד
אסיק. gud assik. We have the principle about the גוד אסיק gud
assik extending wall, okay, which is the גוד אסיק. gud assik. And
the point is to say גוד אסיק gud assik you need something
to be ten טפחים. tefachim. You've got to start here, also you
need to start with a real wall. And the question is, what
about the case about מחיצות ניכרות? mechitzot nikarot? And we had two
scenarios about מחיצות ניכרות. mechitzot nikarot. We had one which it's a
platform and they're not obvious to anyone, that רבא Rava says is
no good. We had the other which is a building and it
is an obvious wall to the people in the building, just not
to the guy on top. And that was the question whether the
חכמים Chachamim would say that this case is good or not. Would
the חכמים Chachamim say the case of the roof is good? Can
you say the extending wall when the wall is ניכר nikar to
the people in the building but completely invisible to the guy on
top? And we don't have an answer to that question. Okay, and
that's where we'll end with today.
Go ahead, רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, if the poles are thick
then the poles themselves are the wall. If they are thin then
there is no wall. There is no wall because you don't have
the size of the wall. That would be the issue of פחות
משלושה. pachot mishlosha. Okay, let's look at the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם
Rambam in פרה Parah talks about a case where you have these
poles. If the gaps are less than three טפחים, tefachim, we say
לבוד. lavud. But you still need to have a proper מחיצה. mechitzah.
If the poles are too thin, they don't have the name of
a wall. This is a very important יסוד yesod in הלכות שבת
Hilchos Shabbos and in הלכות סוכה Hilchos Sukkah as well. You need
to have something that is called a wall. If the whole thing
is just thin poles and air, אוויר, avir, then even with לבוד
lavud it might not work because you're starting with nothing. That's what
the גמרא Gemara discusses in סוכה Sukkah when it talks about דפנות.
defanos. We need to have a מחיצה mechitzah that is at least
somewhat substantial.